ILGWU Management Engineering Department Records 5780/118
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Management Engineering Department Records
1941-1982
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/118
1.5 cubic feet
1.5 linear ft.
Records (documents).
This collection consists of records of the Management-Engineering Department of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Materials include files on clothing and textile manufacturers.
5508380
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
T. Dean, July 07, 2009
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 15, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
Created in 1941, the Management Engineering Department was charged with assisting in the improvement of manufacturing techniques and operating methods, as well as providing information on "fair rate pieces," monitoring manufacturing techniques, and providing trainings to workers on efficient operations. Improvements to techniques and methods were made by first observing the ways that operations in the manufacturing of women's garments were executed, and then making recommendations to create efficiencies. The Management-Engineering Department collected information, produced these time and motion studies, and used both to help determine piece rates and develop worker training.
William Gomberg, who had previous worked as a collective bargaining agent with the ILGWU, served as the department's first director 1956. Gomberg eventually became a professor at the University of Pennsylvania's Wharton School, thus his papers are housed at the University of Pennsylvania's University Archives and Records Center: http://www.archives.upenn.edu/faids/upt/upt50/gombergwm.html
Scope and Contents
The records of the Management Engineering Department range from its founding in 1941 to 1980. Included are reports on operations at in specific shops and industries, reports to the General Executive Board about the department's activities, and related materials.
The department's records are not extensive, and do not provide particularly strong documentation of the Management Engineering Department's work. Researchers interested in more information about the Management Engineering Department and its activities may consult reports to the ILGWU international conventions.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Management-Engineering Dept
5508380
- Report to the Education Committee of the General Executive Board, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Convention, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- NACLA Report, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Select Commission on Immigration and Refuge Policy, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Conditions in the Women's Garment Industry, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Management Engineering Department, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Management Engineering Department, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Dressmakers Union - Local 22, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Training Program, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Wilbur Daniels: Memorandum, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- TEECO Tangle Automated Systems, Inc., 1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Industrial Engineering, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Job Satisfaction/Job Performance, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Exquisite Form, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Survey of Typical Equipment, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Scope and Contents
  July 1, 1955
- Management Engineering Department, 1963-1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Management Engineering Department, 1963-1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Management Engineering Department, 1963-1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Management Engineering Department, 1963-1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- National Commission on Productivity and Work Quality, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  May 9, 1977
- Productivity and Incentives, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Productivity and Incentives, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Management Engineering Department Report to General Executive Board; Activities of the Department, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Report to General Executive Board; Activities of the Department, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Memorandum, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Management Engineering Department Report to General Executive Board; Activities of the Department, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Belle Knitting Mills, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Report of the Management Engineering Department to the General Executive Board, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Report of Studies Taken at the Dutchess Manufacturing Company, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Daisy Sportswear, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Report on the Progress of the "Section-Work" System Experiment at the K.U. Dress and Lillian Dress Companies in New York, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Study of Mary Muffet, Inc., 1941 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Blossom Products Corp., 1942 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  March 9, 1942
- Preliminary Investigation of Methods of Production of Lady Youth Company, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Globe Underwear Corp., 1941 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Belle Knitting Mills Report: Management Engineering Department, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Summary Report of Findings at Nardis Sporstwear, Inc., 1942 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Preliminary Report; Management Engineering Department, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Preliminary Report on Appalachian Knitting Mills, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Study of Mode O' Day Corporation, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Report on Real Silk Hosiery Mills, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  September 18, 1942
- Preliminary Study of Operations Performed in the Shoulder Pad Industry, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Report on Dress Department of Carson, Pierie, Scott and Company, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  June 22, 1942
- Preliminary Report of Studies Made at Mayflower Dress Company for Peter Detlefsen, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  July 14, 1942
- The Work-Time Distribution, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- American Cyanamid Company, 1958-1976 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Relationship Between Unions and Engineers, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 25)